<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.13">
  <compounddef id="md__z_richdem_include_richdem_flats_README" kind="page">
    <compoundname>md__z_richdem_include_richdem_flats_README</compoundname>
    <title>Barnes2013-FlatSurfaces</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><bold>Title of Manuscript</bold>: An Efficient Assignment of Drainage Direction Over Flat Surfaces in Raster Digital Elevation Models</para><para><bold>Authors</bold>: Richard Barnes, Clarence Lehman, David Mulla</para><para><bold>Corresponding Author</bold>: Richard Barnes (<ulink url="mailto:rbarnes@umn.edu">rbarnes@umn.edu</ulink>)</para><para><bold>DOI Number of Manuscript</bold> <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cageo.2013.01.009">10.1016/j.cageo.2013.01.009</ulink></para><para><bold>Code Repositories</bold><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="https://github.com/r-barnes/Barnes2013-FlatSurfaces">Author&apos;s GitHub Repository</ulink></para></listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="https://github.com/cageo">Journal&apos;s GitHub Repository</ulink></para></listitem></itemizedlist>
</para><para>This repository contains a reference implementation of the algorithms presented in the manuscript above. It also contains a reference implementation of the algorithm presented by <emphasis>Garbrecht and Martz</emphasis> (1997). These implementations were used in performing speed comparison tests in the manuscript.</para><para>All the programs can be produced simply by running <bold>make</bold>.</para><para>The program <bold>generate_square_grid.exe</bold> makes a square DEM with a single outlet near the bottom-left corner. The grid size is specified as a command-line argument.</para><para>The two reference implementations use the D8 neighbour system to indicate flow directions. In this system all the flow from a central cell is directed to a single neighbour which is represented by a number according to the following system where 0 indicates the central cell. <verbatim>234
105
876
</verbatim></para><para>The program <bold>barnes_algorithm.exe</bold> reads in a DEM file specified on the command line. The file may be generated by <bold>generate_square_grid.exe</bold>, but may also be any ArcGrid ASCII file. The program will time itself and report the results back. The program will print the determined flow directions for the DEM to a file named <bold>out_barnes</bold>. The determined flow directions are also printed as a matrix of arrows to <bold>out_barnes_arrows</bold>.</para><para>The program <bold>garbrecht_algorithm.exe</bold> attempts to reproduce the algorithm described by <emphasis>Garbrecht and Martz</emphasis> (1997). It accepts an ArcGRID ASCII file as a command line input. The input file may also be generated with <bold>generate_square_grid.exe</bold>. Note that this implementation does not apply itself iteratively, meaning that some flats will be unresolvable. It writes the determined flow directions to <bold>out_garbrecht</bold>. The determined flow directions are also printed as a matrix of arrows to <bold>out_garbrecht_arrows</bold>.</para><para>The directory <bold>src/</bold> contains the source code for reference implementations. The source for the improved algorithm is drawn from the RichDEM hydroanalysis package. All code can be compiled by running the <bold>makefile</bold> included in the root directory. Running the BASH script <bold>FIRST_RUN</bold> will compile everything and run the programs.</para><para>At the time of writing, the entire RichDEM code base could be downloaded from: <ulink url="https://github.com/r-barnes">https://github.com/r-barnes</ulink> </para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
